Comic book collection on medical themes
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Supplement 2017, Series III
  - Public health themes, 1951-1990; Subseries 3
    - G. B. Trudeau, You're Smokin' Now, Mr. Butts!, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      "A Doonesbury Book." Published by Andrews and McNeel, A Universal Press Syndicate Company, Kansas City and New York, 1990. Political satire but also containing stories on anti-smoking ("Mr. Butts") and AIDS. Donated by William Helfand in 2014.
    - Le tresor du parc: Diabete et diabetiques, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      "Edition Medecine et Enfance." Published by Edition et communication medicales, Paris. Text by A. Murat, art by P. Marque. Single story about a diabetic boy. Folder also contains two other French pamphlets in comic format for children, "Elixir et le bon usage de medicament," published by medical and pharmaceutical organizations in 1994; and a story about a boy going to the hospital with his mother to get a shot, published by Astra France. All three are the gift of William Helfand.
  - Other comics, 1963-2013; Subseries 4
    - Cynthia Doyle Nurse in Love, Vol. 2, No. 1, 1963 August (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Published by Charlton Comics Group, Derby, Conn. The first story includes a woman doctor described as "beautiful" and a potential romantic rival to Cynthia Doyle. Cover story is about rabies. BH: "But the real plot is about a woman patient coming to accept her motherhood and the baby she didn't want."
    - Mauled, No. 1: True Stories of People Attacked at the Zoo, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      "For mature readers only." Published by Brian Musikoff and Cheese Hasselberger, Manual Comics, Hoboken, New Jersey. Satirical work claimed to be based on fact with names changed. Each story is by a different author. No medical history stories, but see issue 2. The purchase came with a small-format comic book, "An Axe Fell," by B. Musikoff, c. 2004, purporting to explain why he was writing comic books.
    - Mauled, No. 2: True Stories of Surgical Malpractice, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Published by Brian Musikoff through Manual Comics, Hoboken, New Jersey. "This is a work of satire. All stories are based on fact, however names and faces have been changed to protect the innocent." Each story by a different author. BH: "Not medical history, but certainly part of the public image of medicine in the early 21st century." Another copy of "An Axe Fell," by B. Musikoff, 2003, was included with Hansen's purchase of the issue.
    - Nowhere Men, Vol. 1: Fates Worse Than Death, 2013 November (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Published by Image Comics, Inc., Berkeley, California. Science fiction stories. Eric Stephenson, Writer and publisher, Nate Bellegarde, artist, Jordie Bellaire, colorist, and Fonografiks, design. The four main characters are claimed to be scientists and physicians.
  - Reference sources on comic books, 1996-2012; Subseries 5
    Published works donated by Bert Hansen. A book, also donated by Hansen, Bradford W. Wright, Comic Book Nation: The Transformation of Youth Culture in America (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001), was transferred to the Historical Library's circulating collection.
    - Bert Hansen, "True Adventure Comic Books and American Popular Culture in the 1940s: An Annotated Research Bibliography of the Medical Heroes", 2004 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      In International Journal of Comic Art 6/1 (Spring 2004): 117-147. Entire issue donated. Folder also contains annotated copies of the article listing which titles Hansen donated to the Historical Library.
    - Bert Hansen and Boaz Adler, "Stories of the Great Chemists", 2012 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      In: Chemical Heritage 30/1 (Spring 2012): 20-25. Whole issue is included. Comic book stories on medical history published in Mexico and read across Latin America on such chemists as Antoine Lavoisier, Humphry Davy, Marie Curie, and Louis Pasteur.
    - Reinhold Reitberger and Wolfgang Fuchs, Comics: Anatomy of a Mass Medium, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Published by Little, Brown and Company, Boston, in 1971.
    - Robert M. Overstreet, The Overstreet Comic Book Price Guide, 26th ed., 1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Published by Avon Books, New York, 1996. Contains a price guide for issues of comic books from 1897 on.